If I want to change this into something
else, turn this into a rhythm electric
guitar. [music]
Ooh,
it's so good. We've added something that
I think is really [music] special to
Studio 2, the ability to imagine your
own plugin.
[music]
Hey everyone, welcome back to the
channel. My name is Luke and today we
are going to be talking about a massive
update to Sunno Studio and I am joined
by Henry Fipps, the product manager of
Studio. Thanks Luke, happy to be here.
All right, so Henry, for producers, what
was the main goal about building this?
We got a lot of feedback that people
miss the parts of their workflow that
they're familiar with from other
platforms. Things like real-time audio
effects where you can put a reverb on a
vocal or something. MIDI input where you
can play on a keyboard and, you know,
play out a melody or a chord idea. These
are things that have been around for a
long time. And the reason they've stuck
around is because they're awesome. Um,
and they're very expressive ways to make
music and people understand how they
work. So, Studio 2 is really about
bringing some of these existing music
production techniques into a space where
they can kind of interact with some of
the new technology that we're bringing
to music production. [music]
We also built in sort of this like
studio assistant. We call it studio
chat. And it's a chat bar that lets you
talk directly to your DAW project. And
that's aware of all of the audio effects
that are on your tracks. it's aware of
your MIDI and stuff. And so the goal is,
you know, bring in a bunch of
conventional music production
techniques, but make them much more
accessible by including natural language
as a way that you can talk to all these
things. So here we have a studio project
that I made. I know that there's a lot
going on here. Um, but the chat is these
little sparkles down here. So I can
click to open it up and I can also just
press enter at any time to make it
appear. And the idea here is that it's,
you know, one little button press away.
rename all my tracks to something that
makes more sense. So, in this case, I'm
doing something that a lot of producers
have asked about directly, actually,
like can we just have AI to help like
clean up my session and rename things
and color code things? Like, the answer
is yes, we absolutely should. Um, so
this can see the project state. It knows
the audio that's on all of the tracks
and so it can help you clean up your
project and it can also, you know, it
still has the musical brain of Seno
inside of it as well. So it can uh
create new audio tracks directly onto
the timeline as well. So I can say like
add a baseline here.
Should be 70s inspired
and
electric bass.
[music]
You can ask it questions about how
things work. You could say, "How do I
record into this?" And it should give
you a response that teaches you which
buttons to click in order to start
recording your audio.
>> Wow. The idea is that it feels like a
studio assistant who's right there next
to you teaching you how to use the
product um and helping you along the
way. [music]
First, what is MIDI? MIDI is the
language for expressing notes over time,
the digital language for that. You'll
see that we've got like audio tracks on
this timeline that look like this, where
we've got these squiggly waveforms, and
these are familiar to most Sunni users
at this point. Um, but you'll now see
another type of track that has these
horizontal lines. These represent notes.
Um, and you can think of them like notes
on a piano. And you can play these in
with an external keyboard or you can
play these in with your computer
keyboard. So, we can pull up this little
graphic. We refer to this as musical
typing. And I can play
[music]
um yeah, you can play chords on your
laptop. Um, and or little melodies if I
wanted.
Oops. [music]
And this is so fun because like the
ultimate goal of all of this is to allow
you to express the idea that you have.
Um, and that often involves very
specific chord patterns or very specific
even voicings of chords. Like not all G
major chords are created equal, right?
There's different ways to play them. And
so with MIDI, you can finally get
really, really precise. And then with
Suno, you can take that MIDI clip and we
have MIDI instruments which allow us to
hear those clips. Yeah. Or you can ask
the chat, hey, turn this MIDI clip into
audio, a string quartet, a rhythm guitar
part, whatever it is, and it will go
ahead and like convert that MIDI into
essentially an audio recording.
If you have something like this, um,
this is a MIDI keyboard and you can play
notes. Um, there's a bunch of different
types of MIDI devices, things with
little like, you know, pads that you can
hit, knobs, faders, and Studio supports
all of this. So, you can play stuff in
with the keys, and you can map these
faders and knobs and, you know,
Launchpad buttons to various parameters
inside of Studio.
>> Cool. So, let's show it. Just can we put
that on?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. And I don't have to do much. Just
plug it in. Lights are on. And
[music]
and then can you record that onto the
timeline? [music]
>> Yeah, I can. So, let's um I mean I got
some stuff down here already, but I will
solo this track.
There we go. I've got my recording in
here now. I can play it back. And
there's a little like note flub right
there. That one. Um, and if I wanted
this melody to go, [music and singing]
I can
um, and I don't actually like that
little frill thingy. I'm going to extend
these ones out. So, this is going to be
really familiar to music producers who
have worked in other sort of DAWs, but
uh, as far as Puno goes, this is brand
new to us that you can directly control
the notes and the chords that are on the
timeline here. And then um if I want to
change this into something else, I can
go ahead and you know select this and
say turn this into a
rhythm electric guitar part.
Ooh, [music]
let's go.
It's so good.
All right, let's talk about tracking
live audio. Is there anything new in
Studio 2.0?
>> Yeah. Um, we've added just two small
things. We have a latency calibration
now, uh, which enables you to basically
record your audio in a way that it lands
on the timeline exactly how you recorded
it, which is which is nice. And then we
also have a count in pre-roll, so you
can hear those metronome clicks before
you start recording. Um, which is nice.
Yeah, little just small things, but
makes a big difference. [music] When you
call me in the night
to get back
and I see you walking [singing]
feel.
>> Wow, this is fun. [music]
>> When you call me [singing] in the night.
Yeah, this very like retro sounding.
Okay, let's record it. Let's record it.
>> Let's go.
>> First, I'm going to do the latency
stuff. So, I'm going to pull down this
menu latency.
And so it's clicking and listening back
to it to basically see what the round
trip latency is there. Let me do a count
in one bar. Great.
[singing]
[music]
And your voice [music] in my ear. It
feels so right
when you call me.
So that light quality not great on the
laptop, but um here I'll I'll pop the
headphones back out again. That's great.
So you can hear I'm going to turn the
volume up on this clip. Call me human
and your voice so soft in my ear. It
feels so [music] right
when you call.
>> Keep the lyrics
the same but cover this into a new lead
vocal performance.
Okay, we'll give this a rock. So yeah,
right now it's covering it, which means
that in place it's going to replace the
audio with new audio that has the same
timing and melody.
>> That's right. Yeah. [music and singing]
>> Oo, cool harmonies. Very cool.
[singing and music]
>> Good timing not there, but
>> yeah, it's very cool. I've completely
derailed this video.
>> No, no, no.
>> Luke had one plan and we're going
somewhere else now.
>> [laughter]
>> When you call me in [music] the night
and your voice soft,
>> I love it. Let's chat just really
quickly about people that want to bring
their old projects into Studio 2.0. How
does that transition work? Are there new
features in Studio 2.0 that they
wouldn't have had in the first version
of Studio? Yeah. So 2.0 is totally
backwards compatible with 1.0. So all of
your projects the next time you open it,
you will see a little like modal and
it'll say, "Hey, do you want to open
this in the old interface or do you want
to open this in the new interface?"
>> Um, and we've given you that choice
because, you know, if you have if you're
working on a big project and your
deadline is tomorrow, we want to make
sure that you can still use the thing
that's familiar to you, right?
>> Um, but if you open it in the new
interface, it'll open totally normally.
And all of the features we've added are
new uh and on top of the Studio One
features. So, we're not losing anything
there. Um, so the project will still
load, but there's now just a bunch more
stuff you can do to that audio.
>> Yeah. One of the things is advanced
split, right?
>> Yeah. So, we have a new stem splitter
that we launched kind of recently, and
it offers this advanced split mode that
lets you specify exactly which
instruments you want to pull out of the
mix. So in the case where I had the
vocal here that had those extra things
in its
right, [music]
>> if I want to just pull out the vocal, I
can say get stems advanced split lead
vocal and it's going to go ahead and
just pull out that lead vocal in a very
clean way and give me the option to
arrange it directly onto the timeline.
And I know that in theory it seems like
we ought to be able to detect all the
instruments that are there. But we found
that this works the best when you're
using your ears and you say, "I want
that specific instrument, right?" Even
though it's more work, the stems that
come out of that mode are higher
fidelity and they sound really good. So
for me, I'm always using that advanced
split mode. Okay. So here's that vocal
by itself.
[music and singing]
>> So yeah, that's super clean. Yeah, very
clean. And then if I click insert, it'll
fly right into the timeline or right
below where the original audio used to
live.
>> One of my favorite features in Studio is
remove effects. Can you talk about
remove effects?
>> Yeah, remove effects. Um, yeah, this is
a way just to kind of post-process audio
to try to get the dry signal back out.
So, I can rightclick say remove effects
and it's going to arrange the audio uh
that is dry. So, let's let's give this
>> Yeah, that's that's dry. And this will
work on audio that you bring in here
too. So if you have a vocal stem that
you've sung and has been processed or
whatever and you bring it into studio
and you split out the vocal, you can you
can use this to basically remove those
effects and then uh with the in-house
effects, you can add different effects
back on uh to your to your liking, to
your taste. Very awesome. Yeah, very
cool.
Okay, so one thing that we haven't
talked about yet is the builtin new
effects into Studio 2.0. Oh, no. So,
let's talk about that.
>> Yeah, let's do it. This is something
that I made a few days ago while I was
testing this. And it sounds like this.
[music]
>> Yeah, it's kind of funky. It's groovy.
And the whole thing is like it's got
this movement to it. And the way that
I've been able to do that here is is
using some of our built-in audio
effects. We've got the bass. We've got
these drums that are muted here, but
it's important that they're actually
still on the timeline. [music]
And uh let's open up this MIDI pad right
here.
So, you'll immediately notice when I
double click on the track title, this
little bottom panel pops up. We still
have the panels sort of mapped to those
same keyboard shortcuts as in Studio
One. So, uh, right now two opens and
closes this. Three opens and closes
automation. One moves the chat around,
and four brings the library open,
whatever. If I open up the effects here,
you'll see something that looks brand
new to Studio 1.0 users. So, here you'll
see that we have an instrument followed
by a bunch of audio effects. And for
people who are used to producing music
and other DAWs, this will all feel
pretty familiar, but for some, it might
be totally brand new. So, let me start
by turning off all of these different
things. and I will turn them on one at a
time to show you how they work. So over
here on the left we have the instrument
that's actually making this sound. Um it
looks like this. It's a synth
kind of dry and sterile sounding. So the
first thing we're going to do is we're
going to add a reverb. And I've already
got one here. But the way this looks is
you press the add audio effects button
and you get this picker where you can
basically choose effects. And I expect
that we'll be adding a lot more uh over
time. But we have this reverb. Let's
turn it on and see how it sounds.
[music] So already we're starting to add
a little bit of space, a little bit of
that room noise. Um a delay takes the
signal and basically like repeats it. So
it's like a little slap effect on a
guitar or something. So I've added that
too just give it more space.
>> [music]
>> Yeah. Um, I added some distortion,
just kind of like a little bit of like
crunchiness. [music]
And then we have the compressor. And I
know we've made other videos maybe here,
here, somewhere. Link down below.
>> Exactly. Link down below. Um, where you
can learn more about how it works. But I
have selected a side chain input for
this compressor, which means that the
synth is going to respond to one of the
other instruments on the timeline. In
this case, I've chosen the drums. So,
take a listen to what happens when I
turn the compressor on here. So, [music]
this is off
and here's on.
[music] I'll make it even more dramatic
by pulling the threshold down.
>> It kind of like dances to those drums.
Um, and this is a super important part
of a lot of music production. So, if I
turn on the drum and bass, [music]
>> [music]
>> It kind of glues all these things
together, which is nice.
>> Side chain compression, right?
>> Side chain compression in this case.
Yeah. And then finally, I've got an EQ
on this track, which um controls the
frequency balance, and I'm using it to
muffle the sound. Um and I'm actually
changing how muffled it is over time,
which is a fun fun thing to do as well.
So, I'll turn it on.
And let me actually take this as an
opportunity to showcase automation as
well. Automation is the ability to
change the way these parameters are over
time. So if I go back here,
[music]
yeah, we're changing where that filter
is happening over time to allow the
synth to like come in in a fun like
dramatic cool way to the song. All of
these things just add up to way more
ways to control the sound on the
timeline. And it also is the beginning
of being able to make music in Sunno in
a tactile way where you get to like turn
a knob and actually hear the effect in
real time. Um, so I'm very excited that
we've been able to pull in some real
time creation elements to Studio 2.0.
All right, so there are some built-in
plugins, but can you make custom
plugins?
>> Yeah, let me show you. Okay, so we
talked about all of the different
plugins that are in this list, right?
And there's a bunch. I think we have uh
seven right now, but there's more
coming. Okay,
>> but let's say there's a plugin that you
really miss from your old production
workflow or maybe you've always had an
idea for a plugin that you want to
exist, but you don't know how to make
it. Um, we've added something that I
think is really special to Studio 2,
which is the ability to imagine your own
plugin. Something that I'm missing is a
tremolo. Um, a lot of old like keyboards
and organs have like a wa like type
thing. So, let's try to make one of
those. Make me a new plugin that
does a tremolo effect. I want it to be
like those old organ rotary cabinets. I
should be able to control the speed and
the depth, which in plug-in language is
kind of like the amount. I could
probably write amount. Um, this is all
natural language, so it'll it'll kind of
figure it out. But let's start there and
see what happens.
So, right now it's thinking um if I
press this button or if I press one on
my keyboard, I can fly this panel over
to the left hand side where I'll be able
to see the whole conversation history.
Um so, this lets me, you know, if I'm
doing something more involved like this,
sometimes I want to be able to talk back
and forth a little bit more freely.
Okay, so Studio has responded. It says,
"Here's my build plan for the rotary
cabinet tremolo plugin. It's going to
simulate a vintage rotary speaker
cabinet. Um, it's going to have a
dual LFO system. One for the slow bass
rotor and one for the faster. I didn't
know that they split bass treble. That's
cool.
>> That's cool.
>> Um, and then there's going to be a speed
control and a depth control and a slow
fast switch. Oh, that's classic. Those
old organs. Let's build it.
>> Okay, so it is done thinking. It's done
its whole build process. It created a
plugin called Rotor Glow. And I'm going
to drag it onto this track.
>> It even named it for you.
>> It even named it. Yeah. Okay. So, the
interface is pretty simple. Um, over
time, I expect that these UIs will get
more interesting, but we've got our
knobs. We've got speed, depth, warmth,
which I'm not sure what that's going to
do, but I'm excited to hear it. Um, mix,
and then we have our slow, fast switch.
Let's, uh, let me solo this, and let's
hear it.
[music]
And let's turn the depth up [music]
versus not. That's dry. And here's with
[music] rotor glow.
Rotor glow.
>> It's definitely doing something. [music]
I'm hearing it kind of like pan left to
right, too, which is fun.
It's got some like D-one going.
>> Ooh, the warmth is a saturation.
>> Oh, that's fun. I actually like that.
[music]
>> Oh, very cool.
Awesome. Yeah, that's awesome. And so
now this plugin is forever in my
library. Um, so if I go to add a new
audio effect, I can see that in my
plugins now, which is this new section,
I have rotoglow. I can go ahead and add
it to future things. Um, there's also a
way to iterate on these. So I can
continue to refine Roerlow over time.
The possibilities here are very, very
broad. Yeah, anything you can think of,
you can give it a try and over time
build your own personal library of
plugins that only you have that respond
in cool ways to audio [music] signals.
So, just to wrap up the whole workflow
side of things, what sort of quality of
life updates have been added?
>> Yeah, great question. So, I guess the
main stuff is that we've made this whole
timeline just way more snappy and
responsive. Like, these things, you
know, render really fast. You can have a
bunch of tracks here. The audio playback
stays smooth. So, yeah, it's just
starting to feel like a really powerful
engine for music creation. You know me,
I also love my keyboard shortcuts. So,
we've kept a lot of focus on those. We
still have those number keys up top to
open and close the various panels. So
down below here, two opens and closes
the what we call uh like the device view
or the signal chain. I can shift tab to
open the piano roll instead. Uh three
opens and closes like the next little
panel on top for automation or those
take lanes. And then four opens and
closes the library here on this right
side. All of these combined make it
really quick to pop open and close these
various panels and keep your workflow
moving super fast. And then finally,
that chat is just key. I can click on
anything, press enter, and immediately
say, turn this into something else. And
being able to just quickly and then
escape closes that chat. So, being able
to enter and escape really quickly to
just bring this up, type in your
instruction, and then close it out
allows you to keep moving quickly uh and
stay in the flow, which staying in the
flow is ultimately the goal. Okay, so
this is a really awesome update, and
there's a lot of information. And so
we've made a playlist of videos that is
linked down below that will cover each
individual topic on studio [music] more
in depth. Until next time everyone.
Thank you so much for watching and we'll
see you in the next one. Bye.